[Music]
I've always been surprised that I've
been able to teach what I've been
teaching in the Universities because
I've always regarded it as crazily
radical in a sense you know it's crazily
radical in a conservative way I don't
know what to make of that your teaching
is crazily radical in a conservative way
yeah I mean it's in a conservative way
because I think that the past is not
only has value its we cannot live
without the integration of the past no
more than you can live as an individual
without integrating your past
I mean we're historical creatures right
and and we without if we're not united
can't consciously with the past then
were divided internally and socially and
that has consequences so some of them
are playing it themselves out in the
political divisions in the current world
but the consequences can be fatal so you
know what's the saying a house divided
amongst itself cannot stand
right exactly and the house is a very
very to the degree that any symbol is
universal the house is a pretty
universal symbol for the for the
structure of the psyche so yeah and
flowing on from that it's interesting to
hear you call it radical conservatism
because there's a few quotes that you
that I've transcribed that from the
ideology logos and belief lecture which
I remember having a kind of hair stand
up on the back of my neck moment when I
heard you say this I don't know what
happens to a person if they bring
themselves completely into alignment
I've had intimations of what that might
mean we don't understand the world very
well we don't understand her world could
be mastered if it was master completely
we don't know how an individual might
manage that we don't know what
transformations that might make possible
that's that's mysticism rather than
religion is it not well I don't know if
you can you could draw a distinction
between those two things to some degree
because you could say that in a
religious system there's two components
and people are temperamentally inclined
to align with one or the other there's a
dogmatic component so the Conservatives
are more
likely to align with that and there's a
active mystical component which updates
the conservative component but also
threatens it so which is what creative
thought does in general and so I would
say that the mystical element of that is
religious but it's more on the
transformative side but you know I also
think that figures like the Buddha you
know he's an exemplar of the
possibilities of that alignment and the
exercise is the yogic exercises for
example our attempts to bring that
alignment into being you know I mean
it's very centred on the body which is
quite interesting even though it's a
spiritual tradition right it's very very
centered on the body and I suppose
that's related to the idea of the the
Christian idea and the Jewish idea for
that matter but the Christian idea more
particularly of the sacredness of the
body and also the Christian insistence
that in the universal resurrection the
body will also be resurrected right it's
not and you know people are cynical
about that idea but but there's a you
know because they think about it as
simplistic and and archaic and
superstitious and all of that and
they're missing the point the point is
that that system doesn't denigrate the
body it's as the body there's something
about the body that's integral to being
and cannot merely be disposed of and and
and so if there's a eternality to
existence then it's an embodied
eternality and that's not especially
given what we know now about the manner
in which mmm intelligence operates is
it's not really possible to have a
disembodied being it's not possible
really so yeah when you say you have
intimations of what that might mean can
you explain what you mean by that
well I've had experiences where
everything came together you know and
and and there are very very powerful
experiences and and they're they're also
characterized by it's like everything
turns into a musical symphony where each
part is exact
appropriate for that moment and and I
think music actually expresses that
which is partly why music produces
transcendent experiences you know when
people are dancing to something profound
and they're really into it let's say the
music and the person are the same thing
and then if if things really get going
you see this sometimes in a rock concert
or a musical concert where everyone is
in the same place right the band kicks
into high gear and they're way out
beyond where they usually go you don't
see that that often in a concert even a
great concert but now and then you
really see it and the whole place is one
thing that's just pulsing you know and
that's an amazing experience and I think
it is an intimation of paradise it's
something like that and you can think
about that psychologically you know
because it also makes sense
psychologically that your optimal
experiences are going to occur when
you're most United with yourself and but
I don't know what see we don't exactly
understand the relationship between our
consciousness and the world the
materialistic notion is that everything
is deterministically causal essentially
it's a newtonian view it's also not true
but we know that it's factually not true
but apart from that or or it's I
shouldn't say that exactly but at the
very base of things determinism isn't
the operative mechanism and I think
things are too complex actually to be
strictly determined and it does look to
me like we negotiate through that
complexity but when we're at our best
when we're integrated completely and
there is an effect of that integration
in principle on what we would normally
regard as external reality because
external reality can line up with that
integration as well and so-called
external reality and I think people
probably experienced that when they have
peak sexual experiences with someone you
know where there's real intimacy because
they're in the same place at the same
time and it
everything comes together for that
moment you know maybe literally yes yes
literally right and and and I also don't
think that that linguistic usage is
chance right because I think that's a
place where that experience is a brief
intimation of of heaven that might be a
way of thinking about it so well through
listening to it started to make sense of
a lot of what I've been doing over the
last few years I've done quite a lot of
sort of deep transformational practices
a lot of shadow works of integrating the
shadow and actually feeling that real
sense of becoming more in alignment with
myself feeling that these different
parts of myself coming together and
feeling more embodied and more present
in the world but it was through
listening to you that I made this
connection with the logos with the idea
that this is actually a deep principle
of Western culture which gave it another
it's a real it's the Incarnation right
because the Incarnation is is as at
least a symbolic representation of the
idea that the Spirit has to fully
inhabit the body right and that's also a
remarkable
it's a remarkable idea especially
because the spirit so to speak the
psyche if you want flees from the body
in terror because the body is the place
of mortality and suffering and so people
are disembodied and it's because what
one way of looking at is because they're
too afraid to become fully embodied and
it's no wonder they're afraid there's
reason to be afraid but the question is
well what would you be like if you had
the courage to be fully embodied and
that's fully incarnate that's another
way of thinking about that and the idea
that Christian ideas that the fully
incarnate human being is the Messiah
that's the idea that's a hell of an idea
you know but it means embracing the
horrors of the world that's what it
means and that's not only the horrors of
the world but the evil of the world you
know so there's this idea that Christ
took absolutely well then those are
those are not different and you know
there's this idea that not only was
crazy
the incarnated spirit right so fully
descended into the body let's say but
that he also took the sins of the world
onto himself and what that means is that
psychologically speaking is that part of
spiritual development is to recognize
the satanic tendencies that characterize
you and to fully wrestle with them and
to and to integrate them that's the
thing it's it's not so much to cast them
away it's to transmute them you know and
you can see the difference between
people who've done that and people who
haven't at least to some degree because
people who haven't integrated the shadow
at all are naive and you can tell that
when you look at them and you can tell
that when you talk to them and because
they're naive they're often resentful as
well because they get taken advantage of
and someone who's integrated that more
they're dangerous in in the martial arts
sort of way which is they're dangerous
but they don't have to be they don't
have to use it because their presence
radiates what would you say it doesn't
radiate threat exactly well certainly
strength but it's it's it's it's the
potential for havoc that's the right way
of thinking about it there's a there's
an implicit potential for havoc and
that's really necessary it's one of the
things that gives people self respect
this is an interesting thing about the
integration of the shadow because
recognizing yourself as the locus of
evil let's say actually in some sense
gives you far more respect for yourself
strangely enough because the same
respect that you might have for a wild
animal or even a monster it's like and
though so then maybe you learn to treat
yourself differently like I think this
is particularly true with regards to the
discipline of children you know if you
know that you're a monster and that that
will manifest itself in your life
consciously or unconsciously and if it's
unconsciously it's it's it's not good
then you become better at disciplining
children and the reason for that is that
you don't want to expose them to your
dark side
and so if they behave and don't provoke
you which means they'll also behave for
other people then you don't the
monstrous part can stay in abeyance and
then that's great but if you don't
understand yourself as capable of
wreaking havoc and that can be the kind
of havoc that unfolds over decades right
because if you're going to abuse a child
it's the primitive form of abuses the
physical abuse the sophisticated form of
abuse is the continual undermining of
the child's courage across perhaps their
entire life and that there's a terribly
monstrous element to that and if you're
not respected properly by the child say
you will absolutely take revenge on them
and you know that's the holes in some
sense that's the whole Freudian
psychoanalytic story it's not all of it
but it's a huge part of it interesting
that you you say that you have to accept
the fact that you're dangerous or become
dangerous because I'd also say that if
you haven't done that kind of shadow
work if you haven't made friends with
your anger if you haven't integrated it
you're actually more dangerous yes then
things will happen that will it will
come out in a way that you don't expect
right it comes out disintegrated so it
comes out as an autonomous spirit right
under no-one's control and that's like a
burst of rage let's say you know when
you when you hear about a mother who's
done something terrible to one of her
children it's that's the reason is that
you know she maybe she's just been laid
off maybe she went out and had two meant
too much to drink
maybe she's hungover you know she's
she's angry and lonesome and she's
overwhelmed by the responsibility of the
children and she has a child who's
testing and she doesn't know how to
limit it and one day the child tests at
exactly the wrong time and it's like
mayhem and everybody goes well what
happened it's like well seven terrible
things came together at the same time
and produced this outburst of
disintegrated rage and like look the
hell out when that happens you know
so yeah you you want to have that you
you either have that or it has you those
are the options and you don't become
safe by being castrated right that's not
the right move forward and it almost
feels like having done that I feel that
as a as a as a physiological thing
there's more tools at my disposal
it is a physiological thing I mean you
can actually see a change in people's
faces when that part of them is
integrated when the I would say the rage
circuit is integrated because their face
is hardened like they no longer look
like wide-eyed children that they're no
longer someone to who things only happen
there there's someone who makes things
happen and there isn't much difference
between being dangerous and being
indomitable right there.this they're
that they're they're the same thing
looked at from two different
perspectives and so you know in my new
book I wrote a little bit about there
was an idea in the 80s that was
reasonably popular among psychologists
that the way to regulate male aggression
was to socialise little boys like little
girls and that's a very very bad idea
so because suppressing that aggressive
competitive urge which also
characterized as many women by the way
although it's more common among men it
that isn't what you do you you you
integrate it this is why I'm such a fan
of Piaget you know as opposed not as
opposed to Freud but I think Piaget is
developmental model is superior to
Freud's developmental model because for
Piaget the process of becoming civilized
is a process of continual integration
including the integration of what Freud
would consider the in you know I mean
it's not as if for I didn't know that
because he wanted people to incorporate
the it but he you know he kind of
conceptualized socialization as the
super-ego
inhibiting the it'd you know or or
suppressing it
that's only that only happens when the
socialization process is bad when it's
good like if you have a competitive
child like my son was was and is a
competitive person you
have them integrate that into the ethos
of fair play and then it's it's a mark
of character strength at that point
absolutely there's there's no doubt
about it would you would you also say
that that has to be balanced with
compassion with a greatest of openness
as well at the same time it has to be
aimed right you need a name and and to
put your integrated capabilities to work
at bringing everything together is the
right aim and it's not a task for you
know one of the things about I think and
one of the things about the way morality
is taught is it's always taught like
it's your it's your - it's always taught
as if it's your grandma and of course
that is too tight
you know it's a hectoring sort of thing
that you should be good and the reason
that you should be good is kind of for
other people you know and then so it's a
it's almost like the Freudian sense you
told to them yeah that's the super-ego
sense exactly that's right and that it's
a bunch of restrictions on you and and
so you have to reduce yourself in order
to be a good person and that's well you
might say that that's a prerequisite to
discipline because I think in some sense
it is they know that you do have to be
molded and shaped you know Nietzsche
believed that a long period of unfreedom
had to precede a period of freedom and
that's something like discipline but
fundamentally that's not the proper
orientation because making everything
work better is actually the most
demanding task that you can take on and
it's not a matter of reducing yourself
to a domesticated moral being you know
like like a well like a like a fat pug
dog something like that you know it's
it's it's a it's a task that takes
everything that you've got and so you
can use all of those darker forces let's
say to be indomitable as you move
forward and and and you want a challenge
because all of those forces are exactly
the thing that is
therefore the challenge and so it
becomes a matter of well it's a
conversion of something that can be very
dark into something that's a
prerequisite for for light so I was
thinking this on the plane the linking
to the the thing I said before about how
connecting this this personal growth to
the idea of the logos was really
powerful and reframing this and I've
heard you speak about this in a certain
way as almost like a heroic mission you
take on ultimate responsibility for your
words you take on responsibility for
moving the world either closer or
further from chaos that this is really
you take on responsibility for moving
the world closer to heaven or hell and
this I was thinking how powerful a
doctrine of I've always thought I've
made a few documentaries about Isis
before and how seductive a worldview
that is right you can be you can either
be a shelf stacker in water hamster glue
or you're on the frontline fighting for
your culture in an existential conflict
for the future of the world right so
what I find powerful I only really
thought this the last few days is your
message
almost allows you to reframe your own
life in that same heroic way and it
feels like something like that is
essential it is for us to fight back
against those kind of ideologies there's
no doubt about that and it's for the
reason that you just laid out is like
you take a tough seventeen-year-old kid
you know who's rebellious enough not to
fit well into the you know the extra
domesticated school systems that that we
impose on our children you know most of
my my friends cuz I lived in a
working-class town most of my friends
dropped out of school before grade 10
and I wouldn't say it was the least
admirable kids who dropped out you know
these are guys who pretty much
physically matured at 15 or 16 some of
them were pretty big and strong and like
they were done with putting up their
hand to go to the bathroom they were
just done with that and the fact that
they left school you know it was a bad
long-term decision maybe for many of
them I mean a lot of them went worked on
the oil rigs and made a fortune but they
never kept any of it but but they didn't
drop out of school only for weakness
and failure you know and so you there
there has to be there there has to be a
challenge put forward to those people
who are inclined in that aggressive
competitive direction or they will fall
prey to well you mentioned though we
know why would people go fight for Isis
well you you just said why and you can't
really understand that unless you can
allow yourself to imagine how you could
be attracted to that and the Shelf
stacker versus the heroic desert warrior
I mean you know it's an illusion and
it's a dangerous one and it's it's being
utilized in a very manipulative manner
by the people who were who are pushing
this but you always have to give the
devil let's do and do you think we need
a heroic story of our own to combat it
well what do you have otherwise you know
you have a life of pleasure seeking you
there's no you have no admiration for
yourself if you live a life like that
right it's there's contempt their self
contempt that's going to build and and
or or engagement in things at a trivial
level which isn't useful because in the
final analysis whatever your life is
it's not trivial the suffering makes it
not trivial as a baseline you're stuck
you're stuck with a certain number of
profound experiences and all of them can
be negative if you don't all of them can
be negative if you let the default
manifest itself but you don't get
trivial because you have to encounter
your own death and the death of everyone
around you and and the horrors of the
world and so there's no trivial response
that doesn't subject you to that with no
defense and then embittered you so yeah
it's I mean there's there's a call to
nobility in the in the idea of imitation
of the logos but
it's more than that it's a call to
something of well the hypothesis is it's
a call to something of cosmic
significance and I don't think that we
have any right to assume that that idea
is wrong we don't understand our place
in the cosmos and you know if you if you
base your analysis on size physical size
well there are bigger things than us but
it's not-- that's no that's not a
reasonable yardstick there isn't
anything that's more complex than us not
not that we know of so why not use that
as it as a marker and and there is
something there's an integral
relationship between consciousness and
being and that isn't taken with
sufficient seriousness by by the
materialist community they keep like
people like Daniel Dennett for example
and you know he wrote a book on
consciousness which his critics it was
called explaining consciousness and his
critics called it explaining
consciousness away and I book and that
is what he did as far as I'm concerned
and you know people like Sam Harris have
a real hard time with freewill and so
their proclivity is to deny it but they
act out the proposition that people have
freewill including themselves because
otherwise they wouldn't be able to exist
in society because people aren't very
happy when you treat them like they're
not at least semi autonomous ages and so
I don't think that that's fluke I think
that we are semi autonomous agents now
we don't understand how that can be
possible but I'm not willing to say that
it isn't the case merely because I can't
explain it
especially when I observe that people
accept it behaviorally as an axiomatic
proposition so they accept it as true it
can say they don't believe it but it
doesn't matter well it depends on what
you think you mean when you say believe
then for me you act out what you believe
you know and your your conscious your
your
your cognitive your capacity for
abstraction can divorce itself from your
embodied reality and go wherever it
wants it can even propose contradictory
it can propose a worldview that isn't in
alignment with the manner of your
embodiment at all that happens all the
time it happens to everyone to some
degree because we're not transparent to
ourselves but but well UK it isn't so
straightforward to determine what our
place is in the in the world and the
thing that really got me with regards to
that wasn't the good that we could do
but the harm that we can do because you
can debate about the good we can do but
you cannot debate about the arm we can
do that's done we know if we want to
know and I think my experience was when
I took that seriously
which meant understanding how that was
about me you know about that arch which
was about me and that the Stalinist
camps were about me then while that
reorients you that's a deep part of the
shadow idea right I mean and I think
that is part of the idea of taking the
sins of the world onto yourself it's
like you're a human being so you see
what human beings do that's you and you
might say well I'd never do that it's
like don't be so sure about that
in fact you're the probability that
you're wrong is extraordinarily high
well that's yes and I mean it isn't
self-evident that the default position
is heroism in the face of the advance of
evil in fact quite the contrary so it's
highly probable that you would be on the
side of the weak who are transformed
into oppressors and that's a very
terrifying realization if you if you
take it seriously which you
should and I do believe that we if we
don't take that with sufficient
seriousness we are not going to survive
because we're too powerful to be naive
you know and that was something that you
insisted on especially after the
invention of the hydrogen bomb in
particular it's like if you're going to
play with fire you better be a master of
fire what are the prerequisites for true
knowledge and understanding because it
seems to me that intelligence is only a
small matter of seeing an understanding
properly and it takes a certain amount
of moral courage it takes a certain
amount of having done the work of
introspection having done the work of
defense introspection what do you think
the the components are for true
knowledge and understanding well I think
I think the motivation one of the best
motivations is existential terror you
know I mean I don't remember where this
is in the Old Testament but the line is
the fear of God is the beginning of
wisdom and that's definitely
psychologically true but but we could
strip it say of its transcendent
implications and say well if for me
anyways I wasn't motivated to be serious
until I knew what I was capable of in
the most negative way because you don't
take yourself seriously until you know
that you can be you are an evil monster
and you don't take that seriously until
you know what that means
and so but once you know what that means
especially if you do it if you find that
out consciously say then you're in a
position to start taking yourself
seriously enough so that you might be
willing to learn what you need to learn
to become wise you have to see yourself
as an Auschwitz camp guard and you have
to see yourself enjoying it and that
can't just be an exercise in
intellectual simulation precisely it has
to be
dramatic experience you have to feel
that in your bones and then you have to
decide and you have to give the devil is
do there's something very attractive
about predatory power and you might even
say that it's preferable to pathetic
weakness now I'm not saying that but you
could make a case that it is because you
could say that the person who's
pathetically weak would like to be a
predatory tyrant but just doesn't have
the ability and that's well that's a
Nietzsche and criticism of standard
morality I would say but then is there
something higher than predatory power
well yes I mean part of part of Christ's
encounter with Satan in the desert is
precisely that realization because he's
offered the kingdom of the world and and
that means he's offered the option of
tyrannical power and his response to
that is there's something better and
that's wisdom there is something better
and there's no reason not to go for what
is the best what else you don't have
anything better to do than that by
definition right so why not work for the
betterment of being and abandon your
resentment and your hatred of humanity
and your self contempt and and take on
the responsibilities of the horrors and
and catastrophes of of human existence
and do what you can to well at least not
make it worse but maybe to make it
better you know you can you know you can
make it worse and better you just don't
know how much find out it might be way
more than you think I'm sure that's the
case so there isn't any more an
interesting adventure than that you know
find out how much good you can do in the
world and not in it and not in this
moralistic thou shalt not weigh
but in a forthright noble courageous
eyes wide open articulate embodied
manner and then god only knows where we
could get so let's say let's find out
that would be good it's certainly better
than the alternative
don't if you saw the logo that we've put
together forever wisdom and recognize
the eye and yep in the triangle yeah
perfect we were looking for an abstract
kind of way that didn't look too
Illuminati mm-hmm there's a little bit
Illuminati but not quite right so much
yeah well that's the thing is that it's
the it's the Sun in the pyramid that you
worship not the pyramid right because
the Sun is the thing that in both senses
that stops it from being the patriarchy
so that's the thing that you can have a
relationship with that it transcends the
dominance hierarchy so yeah it is it is
it's it's it's it like in the Lion King
that there's that little bird Zazu well
he flies above everything sees
everything that's the eye that's the
Egyptian eye it's outside the structure
it's the thing that moves up and down
the structure and it repairs it that's
what consciousness does in your body
it's it moves up and down levels of of
reality let's say and and alters them so
in its so it's outside the structure and
it's also the thing that gives rise to
the structure but the structure also
gives rise to it that's why there's
Trinitarian ideas in Christianity you
know there's the father and the son and
they're mutually causal think well how
can that be
well the son gives birth to the father
obviously because boys turn into men but
the father also gives birth to the son
and so that's part of the reason that
those Trinitarian ideas exist so
you